What is the Pearson Correlation?
Have you ever wondered if certain things influence each other? For example, if gas prices rise when daily temperatures increase?

With the Pearson Correlation, you can find out.

For two lists of numbers, it returns values between +1 and −1:

1: Y increases as X increases.
0: There is no linear correlation between the variables.
−1: Y decreases as X increases.
The Pearson correlation coefficient is typically denoted by r, Pearson’s ρ or simply ρ.



http://pearsoncorrelation.com/

HR exercise --> Pearson Correlation: 0.612 --> that's a weak correlation (Reason: there is an outliner)
http://pearsoncorrelation.com/#t=&t1=10%209.8%208%207.8%207.7%207%206%205%204%202&t2=200%2044%2032%2024%2022%2017%2015%2012%208%204

Same dataset --> Spearman's Rank Correlation Coefficient: 0.903 --> that's a strong monotonic correlation

A Spearman correlation of 1 results when the two variables being compared are monotonically related, even if their relationship is not linear. This means that all data-points with greater x-values than that of a given data-point will have greater y-values as well. In contrast, this does not give a perfect Pearson correlation.

The Spearman correlation is less sensitive than the Pearson correlation to strong outliers that are in the tails of both samples. That is because Spearman's rho limits the outlier to the value of its rank.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spearman%27s_rank_correlation_coefficient

More resources:

http://www.statstutor.ac.uk/resources/uploaded/spearmans.pdf

Key point
Pearson --> show linear correlation
Spearman --> show monotonic correlation

